<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE page SYSTEM "..\Data\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="..\Templates\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.xsl"?>
<page id="ExclMain" count="1/2">
    <title>Greetings, Interjections and Exclamations</title>
    <introduction>This section considers various types of common utterances which are not complete sentences.  We will deal with greetings, interjections and exclamations in turn.</introduction>
    <form section="excl" transparent="no">
<introduction>Greetings typically consist of a particular word or phrase, either standing alone or followed by a name or nominal phrase describing the peson or animal being greeted.  Those that are full sentences or full questions, such as <example>How do you do?</example> and <example>How are you?</example> and <example>Have a good day!</example> will parse automatically and do not need special treatment here.  We are interested in the following types of greetings:</introduction>
    <EnglishExample>
        <exItem label="1.">Hi!</exItem>
        <exItem label="2.">Howdy!</exItem>
        <exItem label="3.">Hello, Jill.</exItem>
        <exItem label="4.">Goodby.</exItem>
        <exItem label="5.">Good day, sir.</exItem>
        <exItem label="6.">Good morning, Bob.</exItem>
        <exItem label="7.">Good afternoon.</exItem>
        <exItem label="8.">Good evening.</exItem>
        <exItem label="9.">Good night, sweet baby.</exItem>
    </EnglishExample>
<prompt>Key similar examples of greetings in your language here:</prompt>
        <textBox id="ExclGreet" dataItem="greetExample" rows="5"/>
        <br/>
<instruction id="ExclGreetLexiconInstruction">All of these words or phrases (not including the nominal phrases or names) need to be entries in your lexicon.  Those that are phrases need to be entered in the lexicon with underscores between the words so <tool>Join Compound</tool> will parse them as units within <tool>CARLA Studio</tool>.  Either give each one the category <category>Greet</category> in the lexicon, or add the feature <feature>makeGreet</feature> to the entry to assure the proper category for the syntax.</instruction>
<br/>
<introduction>Interjections typically consist of a particular word or phrase that is used alone, usually with an exclamation point following it.  Though many of the words in interjections are not used in any other situation, regular adjectives are also used in this way.  Some examples of interjections in English are:
</introduction>
    <EnglishExample>
        <exItem label="10.">Ouch!</exItem>
        <exItem label="11.">Gross!</exItem>
        <exItem label="12.">Cool!</exItem>
        <exItem label="13.">Jumping Jehosaphat!</exItem>
        <exItem label="14.">Jimminy Cricket!</exItem>
    </EnglishExample>
<prompt>Key similar examples of interjections in your language here:</prompt>
        <textBox id="ExclIntj" dataItem="intjExample" rows="5"/>
        <br/>
       <introduction>‘Yes’ and ‘No’ answers to questions will be treated <span id="ExclYesNoNotPracticalSpan" show="swNotPractical">by the same rule that allows</span><span id="ExclYesNoPracticalSpan" show="swPractical">like</span> interjections.  </introduction>
<prompt>Key the word(s) which can stand alone and mean ‘yes’, such as ‘yes’ and ‘yeah’ in English, here:</prompt>
        <textBox id="ExclYes" dataItem="yesExample" rows="3"/>
        <br/>
<prompt>Key the word(s) which can stand alone and mean ‘no’, such as ‘no’ and ‘naw’ and ‘nope’ in English, here:</prompt>
        <textBox id="ExclNo" dataItem="noExample" rows="3"/>
        <br/>
<instruction id="ExclYesNoInstruction">All of these words or phrases meaning ‘yes’ and ‘no’ and the interjections need to be entries in your lexicon.  Those that are phrases need to be entered in the lexicon with underscores between the words so <tool>Join Compound</tool> will parse them as units within <tool>CARLA Studio</tool>.  Any which are not regular adjectives need to either have the category <category>Intj</category> in the lexicon or have the feature <feature>makeIntj</feature> to assure the proper category for the syntax.</instruction>
<br/>
<introduction>Exclamations typically consist of a particular word, such as <example>how</example> in English, followed by an adjective phrase and usually punctuated with an exclamation point.  English examples include:</introduction>
    <EnglishExample>
        <exItem label="15.">How awful for you!</exItem>
        <exItem label="16.">How nice!</exItem>
        <exItem label="17.">How wonderful that your family could come!</exItem>
    </EnglishExample>
<prompt>Key similar examples of exclamations in your language here:</prompt>
        <textBox id="ExclExcl" dataItem="exclExample" rows="5"/>
        <br/>
<radioGroup id="ExclMTable">
    <groupName dataItem="exclM" default="no">RExclM</groupName>
    <prompt>Does your language have a particular word or words that signal an exclamation (thus making them different than the simple adjectives treated in the Interjections section above)?</prompt>
    <radio id="ExclMNo" dataValue="no">No</radio>
    <radio id="ExclMYes" dataValue="yes">Yes</radio>
</radioGroup>
<prompt id="ExclMPrompt" show="swExclMYes">Key the particular word(s) that signal an exclamation here:</prompt>
        <textBox id="ExclExclM" dataItem="exclMExample" show="swExclMYes" rows="3"/>
        <br/>
<checkboxGroup id="ExclMPosTable" show="swExclMYes">
    <prompt>Where does the particular word or words that signal an exclamation occur with respect to the adjective phrase?  Please check all options that your language uses:</prompt>
   <checkbox id="ExclMPosBefore" dataItem="exclMBefore">Before it</checkbox>
   <checkbox id="ExclMPosAfter" dataItem="exclMAfter">After it</checkbox>
   <checkbox id="ExclMPosBoth" dataItem="exclMBoth">On both sides at the same time</checkbox>
   <checkbox id="ExclMPosOther" dataItem="exclMOther" >In my language, these words which signal an exclamation may occur as follows: <textBox  id="ExclMPosOtherContent" dataItem="exclMOther" rows="2"/></checkbox>
</checkboxGroup>
       <prompt id="ExclMPosNoCheckPrompt" show="swExclMYesandNoCheck">WARNING: You need to check at least one box to describe where the words which mark an exclamation may occur in your language, or change the answer above to ‘No’. In that case there should not be examples in the textbox above.</prompt>       
<instruction id="ExclMInstruction" show="swExclMYes">In the lexicon, add the feature <feature>makeExcl</feature> to each word which signals an exclamation to assure the proper category for the syntax.</instruction>
<instruction id="ExclMEitherRestrictedInstruction" show="swExclMYesAndBoth">In the lexicon, add the feature <feature>excl-initial</feature> to each word which signals an exclamation that only occurs before the adjective phrase and add the feature <feature>excl-final</feature> to each word which signals an exclamation that only occurs after the adjective phrase.  Do not add either feature to any words which may occur either before or after the adjective phrase.</instruction>
        <br/>
        <buttons>
            <button id="ExclMainBack" value="Back" goto="Contents.htm"/>
            <button id="ExclMainNext" value="Next" goto="ExclTesting.xml" gotoNoGrammar="Contents.htm"/>
        </buttons>
    </form>
<showWhen id="swExclMYes">
    <whenRadio button="ExclMYes"></whenRadio>
</showWhen>
<showWhen id="swExclMYesAndBoth">
    <whenRadio button="ExclMYes"></whenRadio>
<and/>
    <whenRadio button="ExclMPosBefore"></whenRadio>
   <and/>
   <whenRadio button="ExclMPosAfter"></whenRadio>
<or/>
    <whenRadio button="ExclMYes"></whenRadio>
<and/>
    <whenRadio button="ExclMPosBoth"></whenRadio>
</showWhen>
   <showWhen id="swExclMYesandNoCheck">
      <whenRadio button="ExclMYes"/>
      <and/><not/>
      <whenCheckbox button="ExclMPosBefore"/>
      <and/><not/>
      <whenCheckbox button="ExclMPosAfter"/>
      <and/><not/>
      <whenCheckbox button="ExclMPosBoth"/>
      <and/><not/>
      <whenCheckbox button="ExclMPosOther"/>
   </showWhen>
   <showWhen id="swNotPractical">
      <whenValue  element="paws" attr="outputGrammar" value="True"/>
   </showWhen>
   <showWhen id="swPractical">
      <whenValue  element="paws" attr="outputGrammar" value="False"/>
   </showWhen>
</page>
