<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE page SYSTEM "..\Data\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="..\Templates\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.xsl"?>
<page id="NPCompounds" count="1/1">
	<title level="2">Nominal Phrases - Noun Compounds, Complements and Gerunds</title>
	<introduction>Many languages are like English, in that they have noun modifiers. Normally, we simply think that all nouns can also be used as adjectives, but a closer look reveals that true adjectives come before the noun modifier, as in <example>large, round [syrup bottle]</example> but not <example>*round, syrup large bottle</example>.  Therefore, we will treat noun modifiers as compound nouns which are written as separate words.<br/>
		<br/>In the English examples above, <example>bottle</example> is clearly the head noun rather than <example>syrup</example>, because <example>syrup</example> is restricting the type of <example>bottle</example>, not the other way around.  In all compound nouns and noun modifier constructions in English, the head is the right-most noun in the series.</introduction>
	<form section="np">
		<prompt>Key one or more examples with noun modifiers or compound nouns written as separate words, plus some written as a single word, in the box.  If you write all noun compounds as single words, key some of those examples here:</prompt>
		<textBox id="NPCompExample" dataItem="compExample"/>
		<br/>
		<radioGroup>
			<groupName dataItem="comp" default="no">RNPCompounds</groupName>
			<prompt>Does your language have any noun compounds or noun modifiers that are written as separate words?</prompt>
			<radio id="NPCompNo" dataValue="no">No, they are all written as a single word with the head noun</radio>
			<radio id="NPCompYes" dataValue="yes">Yes, some are written as separate words</radio>
			<radioGroup id="NPCompHeadTable" show="swNPCompYes">
				<groupName dataItem="compHead" default="right">RNPCompHead</groupName>
				<prompt>In a compound or noun modifier construction, which noun is the head in your language?</prompt>
				<radio id="NPCompHeadLeft" dataValue="left">Left-most</radio>
				<radio id="NPCompHeadRight" dataValue="right">Right-most</radio>
			</radioGroup>
		   <radioGroup id="NPCompHeadMorphemeTable">
			  <groupName dataItem="compHeadMorpheme" default="right">RNPCompHeadMorpheme</groupName>
			  <prompt>In a compound noun that is written as a single word, which noun root is the head in your language?</prompt>
			  <radio id="NPCompHeadMorphemeLeft" dataValue="left">Left-most</radio>
			  <radio id="NPCompHeadMorphemeRight" dataValue="right">Right-most</radio>
		   </radioGroup>
		</radioGroup>
	   <br/>
	   <introduction>Now consider prepositional or postpositional phrase (PP) modifiers (or complements), such as in <example>the large, round bottle [of syrup]</example> and <example>the boy’s letter [to that girl]</example>.  <br/><br/>
		  Think also of examples of genitive prepositional or postpositional phrases that take the place of the possessor, such as <example>those dogs [of his]</example> and <example>the tablecloth [of my mother’s]</example>.
	   </introduction>
	   <br/>
	   <br/>
	   <prompt>Key your examples of pre/post-positional phrases modifying nouns (without the brackets), other than possessor phrases here:</prompt>
	   <textBox id="NPCompPPExample" dataItem="compPPExample"/>
	   <prompt>Key your examples of pre/post-positional phrases acting as the possessor of the noun here:</prompt>
	   <textBox id="NPCompPPPossessorExample" dataItem="compPPPossessorExample"/>
	   <br/>
	   <br/>
	   <radioGroup>
			<groupName dataItem="ppPos" default="unknown" position="yesHeadDiff">RNPPPPos</groupName>
			<prompt>Looking at both of the above text boxes, where does the PP occur with respect to the head noun?</prompt>
			<radio id="NPPPPosBefore" dataValue="before">Before</radio>
			<radio id="NPPPPosAfter" dataValue="after">After</radio>
			<radio id="NPPPPosEither" dataValue="either">Either side</radio>
		</radioGroup>
		<br/>
		<br/>
	<introduction>Another case which may look like a noun and a complement may actually be a gerund or gerund phrase.  This whole phrase occupies a normal argument position, such as subject, object, indirect object or the object of a preposition.  Some English examples in full sentences with the gerund phrase bracketed include:
</introduction>
	<EnglishExample>
		<exItem label="1.">[Studying grammar] is challenging.</exItem>
		<exItem label="2.">He likes [reading Latin poetry].</exItem>
		<exItem label="3.">The receiver showed his worth by [making the catch].</exItem>
	</EnglishExample>
<introduction>Such phrases may be possessed or be modified as well, and sometimes only the gerund stands alone as the head of a nominal phrase, as in <example>the badly wounded</example>, <example>the dying</example> and <example>your following</example>. Therefore, we will allow gerund phrases to occupy the head position in the nominal phrase.</introduction><br/>
		<br/>
			<prompt>Key one or more examples of gerunds or gerund phrases that can take the place of a noun in a nominal phrase:</prompt>
		<textBox id="NPPartExample" dataItem="partHeadExample"/>
		<br/>
<br/>
			<prompt>Now put the gerunds or gerund phrases you keyed above into sentences:</prompt>
		<textBox id="NPPartSentExample" dataItem="partHeadSentExample"/>
		<br/>
		<instruction id="NPCompInstruction">Note that the head of these gerund phrases is categorically a verb, so these are derived nominals.  They will remain verbs in our grammar rules, but need to be distinguished as gerunds so that only the gerund forms of verbs may be used as nouns.   The appropriate features will be added in section <section number="9.2">Basic, Single-Clause Sentences - Inflection Features</section></instruction>
		<br/>
		<br/>
		<buttons>
			<button id="NPCompBack" value="Back" goto="NPContents.htm"/>
			<button id="NPCompNext" value="Next" goto="NPContents.htm"/>
		</buttons>
	</form>
	<showWhen id="swNPCompYes">
		<whenRadio button="NPCompYes"/>
	</showWhen>
</page>
