<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE page SYSTEM "..\Data\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="..\Templates\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.xsl"?>
<page id="CompFeatures">
	<title level="2">Complement Clauses - Examples and Features</title>
	<introduction>The various types of complement clauses shown in the trees represent the argument structure of the verb as well as its syntactic subcategorization.  Therefore, there is some degree of cross-linguistic similarity in the types of clausal complements the verbs subcategorize for.
</introduction>
	<form section="comp">
		<EnglishExample>
			<exItem>First, consider verbs which take only a finite CP (or IP) complement, like:</exItem>
			<exItem label="1.">I believe (that) Jill is my friend.</exItem>
			<exItem label="2.">Jill insists (that) she is my friend.</exItem>
			<exItem label="3.">I know (that) he likes me.</exItem>
		</EnglishExample>
		<prompt>Think of any similar examples from your language and key them here:</prompt>
		<textBox id="CompFiniteExample" dataItem="finiteExample" cols="50"/>
		<br/>
		<br/>
		<instruction>In the lexicon, add the feature <feature>makeC</feature> to the complementizer(s) so it will show up in the correct position in the tree structure.
<br/><br/>
Add the features <feature>sentential embedded_finite</feature> to the lexical entries for the main verbs in the examples.  If one or more of your verbs require the complementizer to be present, also add the feature <feature>embedded_CP</feature> to those entries.</instruction>
		<br/>
		<EnglishExample>
			<exItem>Next, consider verbs which take either a finite CP (or IP) complement or a nonfinite IP complement, like:</exItem>
			<exItem label="1.">I expect that Joe will come to the party.</exItem>
			<exItem label="2.">I expect Joe to come to the party.</exItem>
		</EnglishExample>
		<prompt>Think of any similar examples from your language and key them here:</prompt>
		<textBox id="CompFiniteOrNonfiniteExample" dataItem="finiteOrNonfiniteExample" cols="50"/>
		<br/>
		<br/>
		<instruction>Add the features <feature>sentential embedded_-question</feature> to the lexical entries for the main verbs in the examples.</instruction>
		<br/>
		<EnglishExample>
			<exItem>Now consider verbs which take a direct object as well as either a finite ot nonfinite complement, like:</exItem>
			<exItem label="1.">I will persuade Joe that he should come to the party.</exItem>
			<exItem label="2.">I will persuade Joe to come to the party.</exItem>
		</EnglishExample>
		<prompt>Think of any similar examples from your language and key them here:</prompt>
		<textBox id="CompDPCPExample" dataItem="DPCPExample" cols="50"/>
		<br/>
		<br/>
		<instruction>Add the feature <feature>sentential_with_object</feature> to the lexical entries for the main verbs in the examples.</instruction>
		<br/>
		<EnglishExample>
			<exItem>Some verbs only take a nonfinite IP complement, but the subject may be overt or dropped when it is coreferent with the main clause subject, as in:</exItem>
			<exItem label="1.">I want to come to the party.</exItem>
			<exItem label="2.">I want Joe to come to the party.</exItem>
		</EnglishExample>
		<prompt>Think of any similar examples from your language and key them here:</prompt>
		<textBox id="CompNonfiniteExample" dataItem="nonfiniteExample" cols="50"/>
		<br/>
		<br/>
		<instruction>Add the features <feature>sentential embedded_-finite embedded_IP</feature> to the lexical entries for the main verbs in the examples.</instruction>
		<br/>
		<EnglishExample>
			<exItem>Some verbs only take a nonfinite IP complement and the subject must be coreferent with the main clause subject and dropped, as in:</exItem>
			<exItem label="1.">Joe tried to come to the party.</exItem>
			<exItem label="2.">I tried to think of more examples.</exItem>
		</EnglishExample>
		<prompt>Think of any similar examples from your language and key them here:</prompt>
		<textBox id="CompNonfiniteProDropExample" dataItem="nonfiniteProDropExample" cols="50"/>
		<br/>
		<br/>
		<instruction>Add the features <feature>sentential embedded_-finite embedded_pro-drop embedded_IP</feature> to the lexical entries for the main verbs in the examples.</instruction>
		<br/>
		<EnglishExample>
			<exItem>Some verbs only take a nonfinite complement, but the complementizer 'for' is present when the embedded subject is overt, as in:</exItem>
			<exItem label="1.">Joe would hate for Sue to be at the party.</exItem>
			<exItem label="2.">Joe hates to dance.</exItem>
			<exItem label="2.">I would like to be appreciated.</exItem>
		</EnglishExample>
		<prompt>Think of any similar examples from your language and key them here:</prompt>
		<textBox id="CompNonfiniteCPOrProDropExample" dataItem="nonfiniteCPOrProDropExample" cols="50"/>
		<br/>
		<br/>
		<instruction>Add the features <feature>sentential embedded_-finite embedded_IPpro-dropOrCP</feature> to the lexical entries for the main verbs in the examples.</instruction>
		<br/>
		<prompt>
  Your language may also have other restrictions on embbeded clauses, such as the embbeded verb being in the subjunctive mood or in the perfective aspect.  Key any of those examples here:</prompt>
		<textBox id="CompOtherExample" dataItem="otherExample" cols="50"/>
		<br/>
		<br/>
		<instruction>Add the feature <feature>sentential</feature> to the lexical entries for the main verbs in the examples.  Also add the feature <feature>embedded_subjunctive</feature> or <feature>embedded_perfective</feature> if appropriate for your language.  Other specific restrictions will need to be taken care of after completion of the starter kit.</instruction>
		<br/>
		<buttons>
			<button id="CompFeaturesBack" value="Back" goto="CompMain.htm"/>
			<button id="CompFeaturesNext" value="Next" goto="CompTesting.htm"/>
		</buttons>
	</form>
</page>
