<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE page SYSTEM "..\Data\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="..\Templates\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.xsl"?>
<page id="IPProDrop">
	<title level="2">Basic, Single-Clause Sentences - <i>Pro</i>-Drop</title>
	<introduction>Some languages are <i>pro</i>-drop languages which allow a subject and/or object to be missing.  This is not allowed in English (except for imperatives).  Here is an example from Spanish which means "I buy a book":</introduction>
<EnglishExample>
	<exItem>Compro un libro.</exItem>
</EnglishExample>
	<form section="ip">
		<prompt>Key any examples of <i>pro</i>-drop from your language here:</prompt>
		<textBox id="IPExamplesProDropExample" dataItem="proDropExample" cols="50"/>
		<radioGroup id="IPProDrop4">
			<groupName dataItem="proDrop4" default="no">RIPProDrop4</groupName>
			<prompt>Does your language allow <i>pro</i>-drop of the subject?</prompt>
			<radio id="IPProDrop4No" dataValue="no">No, the subject must be overt in all cases</radio>
			<radio id="IPProDrop4NoImpv" dataValue="noImpv">No, the subject must be overt except in imperatives</radio>
			<radio id="IPProDrop4Yes" dataValue="yes">Yes, <i>pro</i>-drop of the subject is allowed</radio>
		</radioGroup>
		<instruction id="IPProDrop4NoImpvInstruction">In the lexicon, mark any affixes that indicate imperative and any inherently imperative verbs with the feature <feature>imperative</feature>.
</instruction>
		<radioGroup id="IPProDrop2">
			<groupName dataItem="proDrop2" default="no">RIPProDrop2</groupName>
			<prompt>Does your language allow <i>pro</i>-drop of the subject?</prompt>
			<radio id="IPProDrop2NotReally" dataValue="notReally">Not really, but pronominal clitics sometimes attach to the verb and no separate word or phrase is in subject position.
</radio>
			<radio id="IPProDrop2No" dataValue="no">No, the subject must be a separate, overt word or phrase in all cases</radio>
			<radio id="IPProDrop2NoImpv" dataValue="noImpv">No, the subject must be a separate, overt word or phrase except in imperatives</radio>
			<radio id="IPProDrop2Yes" dataValue="yes">Yes, <i>pro</i>-drop of the subject is allowed</radio>
		</radioGroup>
		<instruction id="IPProDrop2NotReallyInstruction">In this case, you have two choices:
<ul>
				<li>If only a few of the pronouns may/must attach as clitics, you can write a CC table pre-pass that will split the clitic into a separate word.  Then add a root entry to your lexicon for that clitic with the category <category>Pron</category> and correct agreement features.  If you implement this option, then choose the appropriate <i>no</i> answer above.</li>
				<li>If you have a number of pronouns that may/must attach as clitics or you do not want to write a CC-table pre-pass, then choose the <i>yes</i> answer above.</li>
			</ul>
		</instruction>
		<instruction id="IPProDrop2NoImpvInstruction">In the lexicon, mark any affixes that indicate imperative and any inherently imperative verbs with the feature <feature>imperative</feature>.
</instruction>
		<buttons>
			<button id="IPProDropBack" value="Back" goto="IPContents.htm"/>
			<button id="IPProDropNext" value="Next" goto="IPContents.htm"/>
		</buttons>
	</form>
</page>
