<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE page SYSTEM "..\Data\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="..\Templates\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.xsl"?>
<page id="NPAgreement">
	<title>Agreement  ****This file not in use***</title>
	<form section="np">
		<radioGroup>
			<groupName dataItem="agree" default="no">RAgreement</groupName>
			<prompt>Does your language have any marking on the adjective to show agreement with the head noun when the adjective phrase is part of a nominal phrase?</prompt>
			<radio id="AdjPAgreeNo" checked="yes" dataValue="no">No</radio>
			<radio id="AdjPAgreeYesAnimacy" checked="yes" dataValue="yesAnimacy">Yes - they agree in animacy (and possibly also in number)</radio>
			<radio id="AdjPAgreeYesClass" checked="yes" dataValue="yesClass">Yes - they agree in class number (and possibly also in number)</radio>
			<radio id="AdjPAgreeYesGender" checked="yes" dataValue="yesGender">Yes - they agree in gender (and possibly also in number)</radio>
		</radioGroup>
		<instruction id="AdjPAgreeYesAnimacyInstruction" show="swAdjPAgreeYesAnimacy">In the lexicon, mark the adjectives that can only go with animate nouns with the feature <feature>animate</feature>. Mark the adjectives that can only go with inanimate nouns with the feature <feature>-animate</feature>.  Do not add any animacy agreement feature to those which can go with either animate or inanimate nouns.  Or, if animacy agreement is specified by an affix, mark the affix(es) with the appropriate feature(s).  (Nouns will be marked in the next section.)
<br/>
			<br/>If your language also has number agreement: in the lexicon, mark the adjectives that can only go with singular nouns with the feature <feature>singular</feature>.  Mark the those that can only go with plural nouns with the feature <feature>plural</feature>.  Do not add any feature for number agreement to ones which can go with either singular or plural nouns.  Note: if your language makes a further distinction for dual marking, add the feature <feature>dual</feature> to the appropriate entries. If the number agreement features are specified by affixes, mark the affixes with the appropriate features instead.  (If your language does not have this type of agreement, simply do not add any features.)
</instruction>
		<instruction id="AdjPAgreeYesClassInstruction" show="swAdjPAgreeYesClass">In the lexicon, mark the adjectives that can only go with a particular class with the feature <feature>class_##</feature>, where ## is replaced by a number between 1 and 99.  It may be the case that the same affixes that mark the class number on adjectives (and possibly articles and demonstratives too) also mark the class number on nouns.  If this is the case in your language, simply add the class feature to the affixes, and all the words will automatically come from the morphological parser with the class number marked.  Any cases where adjectives do not have an affix which marks the class will require marking of the class feature on the particular lexical item in the root dictionary.  (Nouns will be marked in the next section.)
<br/>
			<br/>If your language also has number agreement: in the lexicon, mark the adjectives that can only go with singular nouns with the feature <feature>singular</feature>.  Mark the those that can only go with plural nouns with the feature <feature>plural</feature>.  Do not add any feature for number agreement to ones which can go with either singular or plural nouns.  Note: if your language makes a further distinction for dual marking, add the feature <feature>dual</feature> to the appropriate entries. If the number agreement features are specified by affixes, mark the affixes with the appropriate features instead.  (If your language does not have this type of agreement, simply do not add any features.)
</instruction>
		<instruction id="AdjPAgreeYesGenderInstruction" show="swAdjPAgreeYesGender">In the lexicon, mark the adjectives that can only go with masculine nouns with the feature <feature>masculine</feature>, adjectives which can only go with feminine nouns with the feature <feature>feminine</feature>, and adjectives which can only go with neuter nouns with the feature <feature>neuter</feature>.   Do not add any gender agreement feature to those adjectives which can go with  nouns of either gender.  Or, if gender agreement is specified by an affix, mark the affix(es) with the appropriate feature(s).(Nouns will be marked in the next section.)
<br/>
			<br/>If your language also has number agreement: in the lexicon, mark the adjectives that can only go with singular nouns with the feature <feature>singular</feature>.  Mark the those that can only go with plural nouns with the feature <feature>plural</feature>.  Do not add any feature for number agreement to ones which can go with either singular or plural nouns.  Note: if your language makes a further distinction for dual marking, add the feature <feature>dual</feature> to the appropriate entries. If the number agreement features are specified by affixes, mark the affixes with the appropriate features instead.  (If your language does not have this type of agreement, simply do not add any features.)
</instruction>
		<br/>
		<buttons>
			<button id="AdjPAgreeBack" value="Back" goto="AdjPMain.htm"/>
			<button id="AdjPAgreeNext" value="Next" goto="AdjPTesting.htm"/>
		</buttons>
	</form>
	<showWhen id="swAdjPAgreeYesAnimacy">
		<whenRadio button="AdjPAgreeYesAnimacy"/>
	</showWhen>
	<showWhen id="swAdjPAgreeYesClass">
		<whenRadio button="AdjPAgreeYesClass"/>
	</showWhen>
	<showWhen id="swAdjPAgreeYesGender">
		<whenRadio button="AdjPAgreeYesGender"/>
	</showWhen>
</page>
