<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE page SYSTEM "..\Data\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="..\Templates\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.xsl"?>
<page id="NPArtCase">
	<title level="2">Nominal Phrase - Article &amp; Demonstrative: Case</title>
	<introduction>Some languages mark the case of the nominal phrase by the form of the article and/or demonstrative.</introduction>
	<form section="np">
		<radioGroup>
			<groupName dataItem="artCase" default="no">RArtCase</groupName>
			<prompt>Does your language have different forms for articles and/or demonstratives based on case?</prompt>
			<radio id="NPArtCaseNo" dataValue="no">No</radio>
			<radio id="NPArtCaseYes" dataValue="yes">Yes</radio>
		</radioGroup>
		<instruction id="NPArtCaseNomAccInstruction" show="swNPCaseNom">Since your language has a nominative-accusative case system, in the lexicon:
<ul>
				<li>Mark the articles and demonstratives that go with subjects with the feature <feature>nominative</feature> and those that go with direct objects with the feature <feature>accusative</feature>.</li>
				<li>If you have a set for possessors, add the feature <feature>genitive</feature> to those entries.</li>
				<li>If a particular article or demonstrative can show up in any position, do not add any feature.</li>
				<li>If a particular article or demonstrative can occur as a subject or as a possessor but not as the object of a verb or pre/post-position, add the feature <feature>nominative.or.genitive</feature>.</li>
				<li>If a particular article or demonstrative can occur as a subject or as an object but not as a possessor, add the feature <feature>nominative.or.accusative</feature>.</li>
				<li>If a particular article or demonstrative may occur as an object or as a possessor, but not as a subject, add the feature <feature>accusative.or.genitive</feature>.</li>
			</ul>
		</instruction>
		<instruction id="NPArtCaseErgInstruction" show="swNPCaseErg">Since your language has an ergative-absolutive case system, in the lexicon:
<ul>
				<li>Mark the articles and demonstratives that go with subjects of transitive verbs with the feature <feature>ergative</feature> and those that go with direct objects and subjects of intransitive verbs with the feature <feature>absolutive</feature>.</li>
				<li>If you have a distinct set for possessors, add the feature <feature>genitive</feature> to those entries, but if either the ergative or absolutive set is used for possessors as well, do not add any additional feature.</li>
				<li>If a particular article or demonstrative can show up in any position, do not add any feature.</li>
			</ul>
		</instruction>
		<instruction id="NPArtCaseSplitInstruction" show="swNPCaseSplit">Since your language has a split ergativity case system, in the lexicon:
<ul>
				<li>Mark the articles and demonstratives that occur with nominative nouns with the feature <feature>nominative</feature> and those  that occur with accusative nouns with the feature <feature>accusative</feature>.  </li>
				<li> Mark the articles and demonstratives that occur with ergative nouns with the feature <feature>ergative</feature> and those that occurwith absolutive nouns with the feature <feature>absolutive</feature>.</li>
				<li>If you have a distinct set for possessors, add the feature <feature>genitive</feature> to those entries.</li>
				<li>If a particular article or demonstrative can show up in any position, do not add any feature.</li>
			</ul>
		</instruction>
		<br/>
		<buttons>
			<button id="NPArtCaseBack" value="Back" goto="NPArtDem.htm"/>
			<button id="NPArtCaseNext" value="Next" goto="NPArtPosition.htm"/>
		</buttons>
	</form>
	<showWhen id="swNPCaseNom">
		<whenRadio button="NPArtCaseYes"/>
		<and/>
<whenValue element="np" attr="case" value="nominative"/>
	</showWhen>
	<showWhen id="swNPCaseErg">
		<whenRadio button="NPArtCaseYes"/>
		<and/>
<whenValue element="np" attr="case" value="ergative"/>
		  </showWhen>
	<showWhen id="swNPCaseSplit">
		<whenRadio button="NPArtCaseYes"/>
		<and/>
 <whenValue element="np" attr="case" value="split"/>
   </showWhen>
</page>
