<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE page SYSTEM "..\Data\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="..\Templates\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.xsl"?>
<page id="NPPossessors">
	<title level="2">Nominal Phrases - Possessors</title>
<introduction>The next type of modifier to consider is possessors.  Possession can normally be expressed by a possessive pronoun (to be addressed in <section number="6">Pronouns and Proper Names</section>) or by a full nominal phrase.  Many languages also add some kind of marking, such as the <example>'s</example> in English, as an indication of possession.  These markings are either affixes (or clitics) on the head noun or phrase-level clitics which attach to one end of the whole phrase.  The English marking is this second type, because alongside phrases where the <example>'s</example> appears to attach to the head noun, as in <example>the boy's mother</example>, there are phrases which clearly show that the clitic attaches to the end of the whole nominal phrase, such as <example>the boy that I just talked to's mother</example> or <example>the girl in green's wonderful speech</example>.</introduction>
<instruction>Think about how possession is expressed in your language.  We won't be able to handle pre/post-positional phrases until <section number="7">Pre/Post-positional Phrases</section> and relative clauses within nominal phrases until <section number="17">Fully Modified Nominal Phrases</section>, but examples such as the English ones above will clarify for you what type of possessive marking you have.<br/><br/>
Note also that possessors can be embedded in one another, as in <example>the boy's sister's dog</example>.  Include such an example in your test data.</instruction>
	<form section="np">
<prompt>Key some examples with simple and embedded possessors here:</prompt>
<textBox id="NPPossEmbeddedExample" dataItem="embeddedExample"/>
<prompt>Key some examples with pre/post-positional phrases within the possessor here:</prompt>
<textBox id="NPPossPPExample" dataItem="ppExample"/>
<prompt>Key some examples with relative clauses within the possessor here:</prompt>
<textBox id="NPPossRelClExample" dataItem="relClExample"/>
<instruction>[Note that if your language has a syntactic distinction between alienably and inalienably possessed nouns, this will have to be dealt with later, using the <help href="AdvancedHelp.doc#Possessed">Advanced Help</help> file.]</instruction>
		<buttons>
			<button id="NPPossBack" value="Back" goto="NPContents.htm"/>
			<button id="NPPossNext" value="Next" goto="NPPossessors2.htm"/>
		</buttons>
	</form>
</page>
