<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE page SYSTEM "..\Data\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="..\Templates\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.xsl"?>
<page id="QPCardinal">
	<title level="2">Quantifiers and QP - Numbers</title>
	<introduction>Now consider numbers.  They cannot be modified by the
degree words like the quantifiers can, though they occur in the same
position.  Note, however, that cardinal numbers can be modified by
ordinal numbers and by <example>next</example> and <example>last</example>, as in <example>the first twenty boys</example> or
<example>the next one hundred years</example>.  Ordinal numbers and <example>next</example> and <example>last</example> can also modify nouns directly, as in <example>the third girl</example> and <example>the last boy</example>.  Since these modifiers also act as regular
adjectives in modifying nouns directly, they will need to have the
syntactic category of adjectives plus a feature to distinguish them.
</introduction>
	<form section="qp">
		<prompt>Key the first ten cardinal numbers, each on a separate line and followed by a period, in order from one to ten here:</prompt>
		<textBox id="QPCardinalNumbers1to10" dataItem="cardinalNumbers1to10"/>
		<br/>
		<br/>
		<prompt>Key the cardinal numbers for 11 through 20 here:</prompt>
		<textBox id="QPCardinalNumbers11to20" dataItem="cardinalNumbers11to20"/>
		<br/>
		<br/>
		<prompt>Key the cardinal numbers by tens for 30 through 100 here:</prompt>
		<textBox id="QPCardinalNumbers30to100" dataItem="cardinalNumbers30to100"/>
		<br/>
		<br/>
		<prompt>Key the first ten ordinal numbers, each on a separate line and followed by a period, in order from first to tenth here:</prompt>
		<textBox id="QPOrdinalNumbers" dataItem="ordinalNumbers"/>
		<br/>
		<br/>
		<prompt>Key your examples of nominal phrases containing ordinal numbers here, including ordinal numbers with a noun, ordinal numbers modifying a cardinal number with a noun, and examples meaning the last or next something:</prompt>
		<textBox id="QPOrdinalExample" dataItem="ordinalExample"/>
		<br/>
		<br/>
		<radioGroup>
			<groupName dataItem="ordinalFormation" default="independent">ROrdinalFormation</groupName>
			<prompt>How are ordinal numbers formed in your language?</prompt>
			<radio id="QPOrdinalAffix" checked="yes" dataValue="affix">An affix is added to the cardinal number</radio>
			<radio id="QPOrdinalIndependent" checked="yes" dataValue="independent">They are all independent syntactic words</radio>
			<radio id="QPOrdinalBoth" checked="yes" dataValue="both">Some are formed by adding an affix to the cardinal number but some are independent syntactic words</radio>
		</radioGroup>
		<radioGroup>
			<groupName dataItem="ordinalPos" default="unknown" position="yesSpec">ROrdinalPosition</groupName>
			<prompt>Where do ordinal numbers and the words for 'last' and 'next' occur with respect to the cardinal number in a phrase like 'the first twenty boys'?</prompt>
			<radio id="QPOrdinalBefore" checked="yes" dataValue="before">Before the cardinal number</radio>
			<radio id="QPOrdinalAfter" checked="yes" dataValue="after">After the cardinal number</radio>
			<radio id="QPOrdinalEitherSide" checked="yes" dataValue="either">On either side of the cardinal number, but not both at the same time</radio>
			<radio id="QPOrdinalEitherOrBoth" checked="yes" dataValue="eitherOrBoth">On either side of the cardinal number, or both sides at the same time</radio>
			<radio id="QPOrdinalBeforeOrBoth" checked="yes" dataValue="beforeOrBoth">Before the cardinal number, or both sides at the same time</radio>
			<radio id="QPOrdnialAfterOrBoth" checked="yes" dataValue="afterOrBoth">After the cardinal nimber, or both sides at the same time</radio>
			<radio id="QPOrdinalBothSides" checked="yes" dataValue="both">Only on both sides at the same time</radio>
			<radioGroup id="QPOrdinalEitherSideTable" show="swQPOrdinalEitherorBoth">
				<groupName dataItem="ordinalEither" default="yes">ROrdinalEitherSide</groupName>
				<prompt>Can all the ordinal numbers and/or the words for 'last' and 'next' appear on either side of the cardinal number?</prompt>
				<radio id="QPOrdinalEitherUnrestricted" checked="yes" dataValue="unrestricted">Yes, there is no restriction</radio>
				<radio id="QPOrdinalEitherRestricted" checked="yes" dataValue="restricted">No, there are separate sets for each side</radio>
			</radioGroup>
		</radioGroup>
		<instruction>
			<span id="QPOrdinalAffixInstruction" show="swQPOrdinalAffix">In the lexicon, mark the affix with the feature <feature>ordinal</feature>.  Also, mark the words or affixes meaning <example>next</example> and <example>last</example> with this feature.</span>
			<span id="QPOrdinalIndependentInstruction" show="swQPOrdinalIndependent">In the lexicon, mark each ordinal word with the feature <feature>ordinal</feature>. Also, mark the words meaning <example>next</example> and <example>last</example> with this feature.</span>
			<span id="QPOrdinalBothInstruction" show="swQPOrdinalBoth">In the lexicon, mark the appropriate affix and each independent ordinal word with the feature <feature>ordinal</feature>.  Also, mark the words or affixes meaning <example>next</example> and <example>last</example> with this feature.</span>
			<span id="QPOrdinalEitherRestrictedInstruction" show="swQPOrdinalEitherRestricted">Those which can only occur before the cardinal number also need to have the feature <feature>QP-initial</feature>
and those which can only occur after the cardinal number also need the
feature <feature>QP-final</feature>.  Do not enter either
feature <feature>QP-initial</feature> or <feature>QP-final</feature> on any ordinal numbers which can occur on
either side.</span>
		</instruction>
		<introduction>Further, larger cardinal numbers can be compounds which may be
written as separate words, such as <example>one hundred thirty three</example>.  In many languages, conjunctions are either required or allowed in the compounds.  The position of the conjunction is usually on the same side of the number as the smallest numbers are.  These two facts tell us whether the compound is head-initial or head-final.  For example, English has head-final number compounds because the conjunction appears towards the end of the compound, either before the last number (the ones digit) or the last two numbers in the compound (the tens and ones digits), as in <example>four thousand and three</example> or <example>six thousand one hundred and thirty three</example>.
</introduction>
		<prompt>Key any examples of compound numbers here:</prompt>
		<textBox id="QPCardinalCompoundExample" dataItem="cardinalCompoundExample" cols="50"/>
		<radioGroup>
			<groupName dataItem="cardinalHead" default="after">RCardinalHead</groupName>
			<prompt>Based on these examples, where is the head in the cardinal compound numbers?</prompt>
			<radio id="CardinalHeadInitial" checked="yes" dataValue="before">Initial, the numbers zero through nine occur initially and any conjunctions occur in the initial part of the compound. </radio>
			<radio id="CardinalHeadFinal" checked="yes" dataValue="after">Final, the numbers zero through nine occur finally and any conjunctions occur in the final part of the compound.</radio>
		</radioGroup>
		<br/>
		<buttons>
			<button id="QPCardinalExamplesBack" value="Back" goto="QPDegree.htm"/>
			<button id="QPCardinalExamplesNext" value="Next" goto="QPCatMap.htm"/>
		</buttons>
	</form>
	<showWhen id="swQPOrdinalAffix">
		<whenRadio button="QPOrdinalAffix"/>
	</showWhen>
	<showWhen id="swQPOrdinalIndependent">
		<whenRadio button="QPOrdinalIndependent"/>
	</showWhen>
	<showWhen id="swQPOrdinalBoth">
		<whenRadio button="QPOrdinalBoth"/>
	</showWhen>
	<showWhen id="swQPOrdinalEitherorBoth">
		<not/>
		<whenRadio button="QPOrdinalBefore"/>
		<and/>
		<not/>
		<whenRadio button="QPOrdinalAfter"/>
	</showWhen>
	<showWhen id="swQPOrdinalEitherRestricted">
		<whenRadio button="QPOrdinalEitherRestricted"/>
		<and/>
		<not/>
		<whenRadio button="QPOrdinalBefore"/>
		<and/>
		<not/>
		<whenRadio button="QPOrdinalAfter"/>
	</showWhen>
</page>
