<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE page SYSTEM "C:\FieldWorks\ww\ww\PAWS\Data\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="C:\FieldWorks\ww\ww\PAWS\Templates\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="C:\FieldWorks\ww\ww\PAWS\Templates\PAWSSKCodeMapper.xsl"?>
<page>
	<title>Adjectives and AdjP</title>
	<introduction>In many grammars, numbers, quantifiers, articles, and demonstratives are considered adjectives, but each of them has a different distribution from the qualifying adjectives, so they will each have distinct syntactic categories.  This section is limited to considering qualitative adjectives that express size, color, age, texture, form, or quality.  One characteristic of this type of adjective is that more than one can modify a noun and in general the order of the adjectives can change (with a slight change in meaning due to the scope of the modification).  For example, <example>hard dull brass rods</example> versus <example>dull hard brass rods</example> versus <example>brass hard dull rods</example>, etc.  This characteristic of stacking adjectives will be dealt with in the next section by an adjunction rule which allows recursion.</introduction>
	<instruction>You need to make sure the adjectives in your lexicon will be mapped to the syntax category <category>Adj</category>.  Choose one of the following options, depending on your situation, and check it off when it is completed:
<ul>
			<li>If you already have adjectives marked with the category <category>Adj</category> in your lexicon nothing more needs to be done.</li>
			<li>If you have adjectives marked in your lexicon with a distinct category all their own, but it is different from <category>Adj</category>, go to the <tool>Category Mapper</tool> and map your morphological category to <category>Adj</category>.</li>
			<li>If adjectives are mixed in with another category in the lexicon, you need to add the feature <feature>Adj</feature> to each appropriate entry so the category will be changed.</li>
		</ul>
	</instruction>
	<form transparent="yes">
		<buttons>
			<button id="AdjPMainOK" value="OK" goto="AdjPModifiers"/>
			<button id="AdjPMainCancel" value="Cancel"/>
		</buttons>
	</form>
</page>
