<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE page SYSTEM "C:\FieldWorks\ww\ww\PAWS\Data\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="C:\FieldWorks\ww\ww\PAWS\Templates\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.xsl"?>
<page>
	<title level="2">Nominal Phrase - Article &amp; Demonstrative: Case</title>
<introduction>Some languages mark the case of the nominal phrase by the form of the article and/or demonstrative.</introduction>
	<form section="np">
<radioGroup>
	<groupName dataItem="artCase">RArtCase</groupName>
	<prompt>Does your language have different forms for articles and/or demonstratives based on case?</prompt>
	<radio id="NPArtCaseNo">No</radio>
	<radio id="NPArtCaseYes">Yes</radio>
<radioGroup id="NPArtCaseTypeTable">
	<groupName dataItem="artCaseType">NPArtCaseType</groupName>
	<prompt>Do subjects of intransitive verbs take the same set as subjects of transitive verbs?</prompt>
	<radio id="NPArtCaseNomAcc">Yes, and direct objects take a different set of articles and/or demonstratives</radio>
<radio id="NPArtCaseErg">No, subjects of intransitive verbs take the same set as direct objects, but subjects of transitive verbs take a different set</radio>
</radioGroup>
</radioGroup>
<instruction id="NPArtCaseNomAccInstruction">You have a nominative-accusative case system.
<ul>
<li>In the lexicon, mark the articles and demonstratives that go with subjects with the feature <feature>nominative</feature> and those that go with direct objects with the feature <feature>accusative</feature>.</li>
<li>If you have a set for possessors, add the feature <feature>genitive</feature> to those entries.</li>
<li>If a particular article or demonstrative can show up in any position, do not add any feature.</li>
<li>If a particular article or demonstrative can occur as a subject or as a possessor but not as the object of a verb or pre/post-position, add the feature <feature>-accusative</feature>.</li>
<li>If a particular article or demonstrative can occur as a subject or as an object but not as a possessor, add the feature <feature>-genitive</feature>.</li>
<li>If a particular article or demonstrative may occur as an object or as a possessor, but not as a subject, add the feature <feature>-nominative</feature>.</li>
</ul></instruction>
<instruction id="NPArtCaseErgInstruction">You have an ergative-absolutive case system.
<ul>
<li>In the lexicon, mark the articles and demonstratives that go with subjects of transitive verbs with the feature <feature>ergative</feature> and those that go with direct objects and subjects of intransitive verbs with the feature <feature>absolutive</feature>.</li>
<li>If you have a set for possessors, add the feature <feature>genitive</feature> to those entries.</li>
<li>If a particular article or demonstrative can show up in any position, do not add any feature.</li>
<li>If a particular article or demonstrative can occur as a subject of transitive verbs or as a possessor but not as an object or as the subject of an intransitive verb, add the feature <feature>-absolutive</feature>.</li>
<li>If a particular article or demonstrative can occur as a subject of any verb or as an object but not as a possessor, add the feature <feature>-genitive</feature>.</li>
<li>If a particular article or demonstrative may occur as an object or the subject of an intransitive verb or as a possessor, but not as the subject of a transitive verb, add the feature <feature>-ergative</feature>.</li>
</ul>
</instruction>
		<buttons>
			<button id="NPArtCaseOK" value="OK" goto="NPArtAgreement.htm"/>
			<button id="NPArtCaseCancel" value="Cancel"/>
		</buttons>
	</form>
</page>
