<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE page SYSTEM "C:\FieldWorks\ww\ww\PAWS\Data\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="C:\FieldWorks\ww\ww\PAWS\Templates\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.xsl"?>
<page>
	<title level="2">Quantifiers and QP - Cardinal Numbers</title>
	<introduction>Now consider cardinal numbers.  They cannot be modified by the
degree words like the quantifiers can, though they occur in the same
position.  Note, however, that cardinal numbers can be modified by
ordinal numbers and by <example>next</example> and <example>last</example>, as in <example>the first twenty boys</example> or
<example>the next one hundred years</example>.  Since these modifiers also act as regular
adjectives in modifying nouns directly, they will need to have the
syntactic category of adjectives plus a feature to distinguish them.
</introduction>
	<form>
		<prompt>Key your examples here:</prompt>
		<textBox id="QPCardinalExample"/>
		<codeInfo>go in qtest.txt, too</codeInfo>
		<introduction>Further, larger cardinal numbers can be compounds which may be
written as separate words, such as <example>one hundred thirty three</example>.  In
addition, some languages allow two numbers to occur side by side, such
as <example>two three</example> to mean <example>a few</example>.
</introduction>
		<prompt>Key any examples of compound numbers here:</prompt>
		<textBox id="QPCardinalCompoundExample"/>
		<codeInfo>go in qtest.txt, too</codeInfo>
		<instruction>You need to make sure the cardinal number words in your lexicon will be mapped to the syntax category <category>Num</category>.  Choose one of the following options, depending on your situation, and check it off when it is completed:
<ul>
				<li>If you already have numbers marked with the category <category>Num</category> in your lexicon nothing
  more needs to be done.</li>
				<li>If you have numbers marked in your lexicon with a distinct category all their own, but it is different from <category>Num</category>, go to the Category Mapper and map your morphological category to <category>Num</category>. </li>
				<li>If numbers are mixed in with another category in the lexicon (e.g. adjectives), you need to add the feature <feature>Num</feature> to each appropriate entry so the category will be changed.</li>
			</ul>
		</instruction>
		<buttons>
			<button id="QPCardinalExamplesOK" value="OK"/>
			<codeInfo>OK link to QPOrdinal.htm</codeInfo>
			<button id="QPCardinalExamplesCancel" value="Cancel"/>
		</buttons>
	</form>
</page>
