<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE page SYSTEM "..\Data\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="..\Templates\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.xsl"?>
<page id="PronNP" count="6/8">
	<title level="2">Los pronombres  - Como frases nominales</title>
	<form section="pron">
		<introduction>Los pronombres comúnmente presentarse solamente en el lugar de una frase nominal completa, pero pueden también ser modificados por una frase del partitivo y en algunos idiomas los pronombres se pueden modificar por los determinantes y los cuantificadores, llenando el lugar de sustantivos en esta situación.   Los ejemplos en español de pronombres, de demonstratives o de cuantificadores modificados incluyen los siguientes: </introduction>
		<EnglishExample>
			<exItem label="1.">todos los doce.</exItem>
			<exItem label="2.">solamente él.</exItem>
			<exItem label="3.">apenas dos.</exItem>
			<exItem label="4.">apenas esos pocos.</exItem>
		</EnglishExample>
		<br/>
		<prompt>Escriba ejemplos similares en su idioma aquí:</prompt>
		<textBox id="PronNPStandAloneExample" dataItem="standAloneNPExample"/>
		<br/>
		<introduction>Además, un pronombre, demostrativo o cuantificador puede ser modificado por una cláusula relativa, como en:</introduction>
		<EnglishExample>
			<exItem label="1.">todos que vayan con nosotros.</exItem>
			<exItem label="2.">solamente estos dos que vi.</exItem>
		</EnglishExample>
		<br/>
		<prompt>Escriba sus ejemplos con las cláusulas relativas, incluidos en oraciones simples, aquí:</prompt>
		<textBox id="PronNPRelCl" dataItem="pronRelClExample"/>
		<br/>
		<introduction>Finalmente, estas categorías también pueden ser modificadas por una frase del partitivo (u otra frase preposicional y/o posposicional), como en </introduction>
		<EnglishExample>
			<exItem label="1.">solamente algunos de ustedes.</exItem>
			<exItem label="2.">apenas que muchos de ésos.</exItem>
			<exItem label="3.">solamente ésos adentro allí.</exItem>

		</EnglishExample>
		<br/>
		<prompt>Escriba sus ejemplos aquí:</prompt>
		<textBox id="PronNPPartitiveExample" dataItem="partitiveExample"/>
		<br/>
		<radioGroup id="PronNPPartitiveTable">
			<groupName dataItem="partitivePos" default="unknown" position="yesHeadDiff">RPronNPPartitive</groupName>
			<prompt>¿Dónde se presentan las frases preposicionales y/o posposicionales opcionales con respecto al pronombre, demostrativo, cuantificador o número?</prompt>
			<radio id="PronNPPartBefore" dataValue="before">Antes</radio>
			<radio id="PronNPPartAfter" dataValue="after">Después</radio>
		</radioGroup>
		<br/>
		<introduction id="PronDistributionIntro" show="swNotPractical">This distribution discussed for English can be accounted for if we allow pronouns, demonstratives, quantifiers, and numbers to be NPs (rather than DPs) in the tree structure given at the beginning of <section number="5">Simple and Possessed Nominal Phrases</section>.  However, some languages allow pronouns to be modified by possessors and adjectives as well, so the correct category in that case is N.  A few languages may require pronouns to stand alone without any modification at all, making them DPs.  Possessive, reflexive, and reciprocal pronouns are always DPs, since they must stand alone.  Consider only personal pronouns and demonstratives, quantifiers, and numbers in answering below.</introduction>
		<br/>
		<radioGroup id="PronDistributionRadioGroup" show="swNotPractical">
			<groupName dataItem="pronounCat" default="NP">RPronNPCat</groupName>
			<prompt>Which category or level in the tree structure is correct for personal pronouns (and other elements which can occur without a head noun) in your language?
</prompt>
			<radio id="PronNPCatNP" dataValue="NP">NP, like in English, because they can be modified by degree words, demonstratives, articles, relative clauses and PPs, but not by possessors or adjectives</radio>
			<radio id="PronNPCatN" dataValue="N">N, because they can be modified by all the same categories as nouns can</radio>
			<radio id="PronNPCatDP" dataValue="DP">DP, because they must stand alone in the place of a whole nominal phrase</radio>
		</radioGroup>
		<br/>
		<buttons>
			<button id="PronNPBack" value="Back" goto="PronIndefinite.xml"/>
			<button id="PronNPNext" value="Next" goto="PronCatMap.xml" gotoNoGrammar="Contents.htm"/>
		</buttons>
	</form>
	<showWhen id="swNotPractical">
		<whenValue  element="paws" attr="outputGrammar" value="True"/>
	</showWhen>
</page>
