<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE page SYSTEM "..\Data\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="..\Templates\PAWSSKHtmlMapper.xsl"?>
<page id="NPQP" count="1/1">
	<title level="2">Nominal Phrases - QP Modifiers</title>
	<introduction id="NPQPIntroNotPractical" show="swNotPractical">Next to be added to the nominal phrase as we work our way down the tree are quantifier phrases (QP), discussed earlier in <section number="2">Quantifiers and QP</section>.  This means we will be able to parse nominal phrases such as these in English:</introduction>
	<introduction id="NPQPIntroPractical" show="swPractical">Next to be added to the nominal phrase are quantifier phrases, discussed earlier in <section number="2">Quantifiers and QP</section>.  This means we are interested in nominal phrases such as these in English:</introduction>    <EnglishExample>
		<exItem label="1.">just those very few books.</exItem>
		<exItem label="2.">all the boy’s many dogs.</exItem>
		<exItem label="3.">only the first one hundred boys.</exItem>
	</EnglishExample>
	<form section="np">
		<prompt>Key examples of similar nominal phrases in your language here:</prompt>
		<textBox id="NPQPExample" dataItem="qpExample"/>
		<br/>
		<radioGroup>
			<groupName dataItem="qpPos" default="unknown" position="yesSpec">RNPQPPos</groupName>
			<prompt>Based on the data you keyed, where do quantifier phrases (including cardinal numbers) occur with respect to the noun?</prompt>
			<radio id="NPQPPosBefore" dataValue="before">Before</radio>
			<radio id="NPQPPosAfter" dataValue="after">After</radio>
			<radio id="NPQPPosEitherSide" dataValue="either">Either side, but not both sides at the same time</radio>
            <radio id="NPQPPosEitherOrBoth" dataValue="eitherOrBoth">Either side, or on both sides at the same time</radio>
            <radio id="NPQPPosBeforeOrBoth" checked="yes" dataValue="beforeOrBoth">Before the noun, or on both sides at the same time</radio>
            <radio id="NPQPPosAfterOrBoth" checked="yes" dataValue="afterOrBoth">After the noun, or on both sides at the same time</radio>
            <radio id="NPQPPosBothSides" checked="yes" dataValue="both">Only on both sides at the same time</radio>
            <radioGroup id="NPQPPosEitherorBothTable" show="swNPQPPosEitherorBoth">
                <groupName dataItem="qpEither" default="unrestricted">RNPQPPosEitherorBoth</groupName>
                <prompt>Can all the quantifier phrases appear on either side of the nominal phrase?</prompt>
                <radio id="NPQPPosEitherorBothUnrestricted" dataValue="unrestricted">Yes, there is no restriction</radio>
                <radio id="NPQPPosEitherorBothRestricted" dataValue="restricted">No, there are separate sets for each side</radio>
                <radioGroup id="NPQPPosEitherorBothRestrictedTable" show="swNPQPPosEitherorBothRestricted">
                    <groupName dataItem="qpEitherRestrictedNumPos" default="unknown" position="yesSpec">RNPQPPosEitherRestrictedNum</groupName>
                    <prompt>Do all the numbers occur on only one side of the noun?</prompt>
                    <radio id="NPQPPosEitherRestrictedNumBefore" dataValue="before">Yes, all the numbers occur before the noun</radio>
                    <radio id="NPQPPosEitherRestrictedNumAfter" dataValue="after">Yes, all the numbers occur after the noun</radio>
                    <radio id="NPQPPosEitherRestrictedNumNo" dataValue="no">No, some may occur on each side</radio>
                </radioGroup>
            </radioGroup>
        </radioGroup>
        <br/>
        <radioGroup>
            <groupName dataItem="qpAgree" default="no">RNPQPAgree</groupName>
            <prompt>Do numbers or quantifiers carry any marking to agree with the noun they modify, other than <span id="NPQPNumberMarkingSpan1" show="swNPQPNumberMarking">marking</span>
                <span id="NPQPNumberAgreementSpan1" show="swNPQPNumberAgreement">agreeing in</span> number?</prompt>
            <radio id="NPQPAgreeNo" dataValue="no">No, they only <span id="NPQPNumberMarkingSpan" show="swNPQPNumberMarking"> mark number</span>
                <span id="NPQPNumberAgreementSpan" show="swNPQPNumberAgreement"> agree in number</span>
            </radio>
            <radio id="NPQPAgreeYes" dataValue="yes">Yes, they agree in other features (also)</radio>
        </radioGroup>
        <instruction id="NPQPPosEitherRestrictedNumBeforeInstruction" show="swNPQPPosEitherRestrictedNumBefore">The program will mark numbers with the default feature <feature>DP-initial</feature>, so you only need to mark other quantifiers.  In the lexicon, mark those quantifiers which can only occur before the noun with the feature <feature>DP-initial</feature> and those which can only occur after the noun with the feature <feature>DP-final</feature>.  Do not enter either feature on any quantifier which can occur on either side.</instruction>
        <instruction id="NPQPPosEitherRestrictedNumAfterInstruction" show="swNPQPPosEitherRestrictedNumAfter">The program will mark numbers with the default feature <feature>DP-final</feature>, so you only need to mark other quantifiers.  In the lexicon, mark those quantifiers which can only occur before the noun with the feature <feature>DP-initial</feature> and those which can only occur after the noun with the feature <feature>DP-final</feature>.  Do not enter either feature on any quantifier which can occur on either side.</instruction>
		<instruction id="NPQPPosEitherRestrictedNumNoInstruction" show="swNPQPPosEitherRestrictedNumNo">In the lexicon, mark those quantifiers or numbers which can only occur before the noun with the feature <feature>DP-initial</feature> and those which can only occur after the noun with the feature <feature>DP-final</feature>.  Do not enter either feature on any quantifier or number which can occur on either side.</instruction>
		<br/>
		<instruction id="NPQPNumberMarkingInstruction" show="swNPQPNumberMarking">
		   To handle the number marking, we will assume that all numbers are plural by default.  Therefore, only the number “one” needs to be marked with the feature <feature>singular</feature>.  If your language makes a further distinction for dual marking, add the feature <feature>dual</feature> to the number “two”.
<br/>
For other quantifiers, in the lexicon:
<ul>
                <li>Mark the quantifiers that signify the whole nominal phrase is singular with the feature <feature>singular</feature>.</li>
                <li>Mark the quantifiers that signify the whole nominal phrase is plural with the feature <feature>plural</feature>.  This should be most of the quantifiers.</li>
                <li>If your language makes a further distinction for dual marking, add the feature <feature>dual</feature> to the appropriate quantifiers, if any.
                </li>
			</ul>
		</instruction>
		<instruction id="NPQPNumberAgreementInstruction" show="swNPQPNumberAgreement">
		   To handle the number agreement, we will assume that all numbers are plural by default.  Therefore, only the number “one” needs to be marked with the feature <feature>singular</feature>.  If your language makes a further distinction for dual marking, add the feature <feature>dual</feature> to the number “two”.
<br/>
For other quantifiers, in the lexicon:
<ul>
                <li>Mark the quantifiers that only go with singular nouns with the feature <feature>singular</feature>.</li>
                <li>Mark the quantifiers that only go with plural nouns with the feature <feature>plural</feature>.  This should be most of the quantifiers.</li>
                <li>If your language makes a further distinction for dual marking, add the feature <feature>dual</feature> to the appropriate quantifiers, if any.
                </li>
            </ul>
        </instruction>
        <instruction id="NPQPAgreementAnimacyInstruction" show="swNPAgreementAnimacyYes">
To handle animacy agreement:
<ul>
                <li>Mark the numbers or quantifiers (or the appropriate affixes) that can only go with animate nouns with the feature <feature>animate</feature>.</li>
                <li>Mark the numbers or quantifiers (or the appropriate affixes) that can only go with inanimate nouns with the feature <feature>-animate</feature>.</li>
                <li>Do not add any animacy agreement feature to those which can go with either animate or inanimate nouns.</li>
            </ul>
        </instruction>
		<instruction id="NPQPAgreementGenderInstruction" show="swNPAgreementGenderYes">
Add the gender features <feature>masculine</feature>, <feature>feminine</feature>, <feature>neuter</feature> to any numbers or quantifiers (or the appropriate affixes) that can only go with that type of noun.  Do not add any gender agreement feature to those which can go with either masculine or feminine nouns.      </instruction>
		<instruction id="NPQPAgreementClassInstruction" show="swNPAgreementClassYes">
		   To handle class marking and agreement:
		   <ul>
			  <li>It is most likely the case that the same affixes that mark the class number or type on nouns are also used on numbers and/or quantifiers.  If this is the case in your language, the appropriate class feature should already have been added to the affixes in <section number="1.">Overall Typology - Classifiers</section>, so all the words will automatically come from the morphological parser with the class number or type marked.</li>
			  <li>Any quantifiers or numbers which can only appear with a certain class, yet do not have an affix which marks the class, will require marking of the class feature on the particular lexical item in the lexicon.   Mark those elements with the feature <feature>class_##</feature>, where ## is replaced by a number between 1 and 25.  Alternatively, these can be marked with one of the class type features discussed in <section number="1.">Overall Typology - Classifiers</section>.</li>
		   </ul>
		</instruction>
		<br/>
		<buttons>
            <button id="NPQPBack" value="Back" goto="NPContents.htm"/>
            <button id="NPQPNext" value="Next" goto="NPContents.htm"/>
        </buttons>
    </form>
    <showWhen id="swNPQPPosEitherorBoth">
        <not/>
        <whenRadio button="NPQPPosBefore"/>
        <and/>
        <not/>
        <whenRadio button="NPQPPosAfter"/>
    </showWhen>
    <showWhen id="swNPQPPosEitherorBothRestricted">
        <whenRadio button="NPQPPosEitherorBothRestricted"/>
        <and/>
        <not/>
        <whenRadio button="NPQPPosBefore"/>
        <and/>
        <not/>
        <whenRadio button="NPQPPosAfter"/>
    </showWhen>
    <showWhen id="swNPQPPosEitherRestrictedNumBefore">
        <whenRadio button="NPQPPosEitherRestrictedNumBefore"/>
        <and/>
        <whenRadio button="NPQPPosEitherorBothRestricted"/>
        <and/>
        <not/>
        <whenRadio button="NPQPPosBefore"/>
        <and/>
        <not/>
        <whenRadio button="NPQPPosAfter"/>
    </showWhen>
    <showWhen id="swNPQPPosEitherRestrictedNumAfter">
        <whenRadio button="NPQPPosEitherRestrictedNumAfter"/>
        <and/>
        <whenRadio button="NPQPPosEitherorBothRestricted"/>
        <and/>
        <not/>
        <whenRadio button="NPQPPosBefore"/>
        <and/>
        <not/>
        <whenRadio button="NPQPPosAfter"/>
    </showWhen>
    <showWhen id="swNPQPPosEitherRestrictedNumNo">
        <whenRadio button="NPQPPosEitherRestrictedNumNo"/>
        <and/>
        <whenRadio button="NPQPPosEitherorBothRestricted"/>
        <and/>
        <not/>
        <whenRadio button="NPQPPosBefore"/>
        <and/>
        <not/>
        <whenRadio button="NPQPPosAfter"/>
    </showWhen>
    <showWhen id="swNPQPNumberMarking">
        <whenValue element="np" attr="agreeNumber" value="no"/>
    </showWhen>
    <showWhen id="swNPQPNumberAgreement">
        <whenValue element="np" attr="agreeNumber" value="yes"/>
    </showWhen>
    <showWhen id="swNPAgreementAnimacyYes">
        <whenRadio button="NPQPAgreeYes"/>
        <and/>
        <whenValue element="np" attr="agreeOther" value="yesAnimacy"/>
    </showWhen>
    <showWhen id="swNPAgreementGenderYes">
        <whenRadio button="NPQPAgreeYes"/>
        <and/>
        <whenValue element="np" attr="agreeOther" value="yesGender"/>
    </showWhen>
    <showWhen id="swNPAgreementClassYes">
        <whenRadio button="NPQPAgreeYes"/>
        <and/>
        <whenValue element="np" attr="agreeOther" value="yesClass"/>
    </showWhen>
    <showWhen id="swNotPractical">
        <whenValue  element="paws" attr="outputGrammar" value="True"/>
    </showWhen>
    <showWhen id="swPractical">
        <whenValue  element="paws" attr="outputGrammar" value="False"/>
    </showWhen>
</page>
